JAMES K SMITH, Project/Program Management, Agile Consultant, Transformation Lead, RTE, Scrum Master, Al-Automated Backlog Development, Organizational Effectiveness, Software Engineering, Risk Management

Any location considered. jksmith@operational.art, 305-956-6482, 727-458-8359

See my book: AGILE V2 COACH'S FIELD MANUAL, available on Amazon, or free on Github.

My Miro boards at miro.com

Samples from an AI RAG template system I've developed for automated backlog generation, cost and completion forecasting

SAFe Program Consultant (SPC - 24906958-1135): enabled to teach all SAFe certifications (SA, SSM, SASM, POPM, SGP, ASE, ARCH, RTE, SDP, LPM, SP, APM).

Certified Scrum@Scale Practitioner (RSASP-5479328) CSM (504356) CSPO (512533)

Organizational Leadership Summary: 20 years in Project/Program Management, with roles as Director, CTO, VP focusing on Organizational Effectiveness, Risk Management, Process Re-engineering

Technical Leadership Summary: 25 years in Software development, Database design, data migration, mission critical systems, api backends, DevSecOps,Stand-up and management of 1) Functional, 2) Enabler, 3) Subsystem 4) Small, high-autonomy teams

Selected Presentations (authored and delivered by James Smith) available for download from my Github Repo at Github.com:

- <u>A Simple Transformation Plan</u> all you need (plus some patience) to move your company to agile product delivery.
- <u>Ceremonies for High Performing Scrum Teams</u> instructor led by James Smith.
- <u>PI Planning and Future State</u> Your guide for executing PI Planning, but with an eye toward the optimizing the future.
- <u>The 3 Lines Model Done Agile</u> The Institute of Internal Auditors 3 Lines Model adapted to Agile Product Delivery.
- <u>The DoR-DoD Contract</u> Definition of Ready and Definition of Done work together to form a very powerful tool to for great outcomes.

- A System of Risk and Dependency Management James Smith shows how the Value Elaboration Stream, Leadership line-of-sight, and strong Scrum teams are the key.
- <u>Agile organization assessment package</u> Fully programmable assessments for the organization and its delivery teams.
- <u>Burnup chart package</u> Programmable spreadsheet and instructions that provide forecasting for release dates and cost. Suitable for any application that has team velocity data.
- <u>State Gov Challenges and Solutions</u> My experiences and takeaways from working with state gov Medicaid E&E programs.
- This resume on Github.com.

Summary Timeline at a glance:

Organization	Title	Term	Clients or Market
Increase Signal	Owner	Nov 2023 - Current	US C2C for consulting services.
Infosys	Program Management, Scrum Master, Agile Consultant,Transfor mation Lead, RTE, DevOps	Feb 2019 – Nov 2023	Ford Motor, Northern Trust Bank, Voya Financial. Citi Bank, ATT
Grid-Sky Consulting	Owner, Principal Consultant, Agile Coach, Scrum Master, Kanban Admin	May 2015 - Feb 2019	State of Alabama, CSX, L3/Harris, Bank of America
Global Treasury Systems	Director of Development, Treasury Software	2011 - 2015	Treasury software market worldwide
Organization	Title	Term	Clients or Market
Marketron	Lead Developer, TvSCAN	2010 - 2012	TV stations nationwide
DXM Technologies	Executive VP, CTO	2005 - 2009	Security Software Startup
USCertifiedLett ers	Chief Technology Officer	2001 - 2004	US, notable: State of California, State of Nevada, US Postal Service
TapSCAN	Chief Developer	1989 - 2000	TV Stations and Cable Networks worldwide

Professional Experience Detail

Program Management, Scrum Master, Agile Consultant, Transformation Lead , RTE, Devops Automation Infosys Feb 2019 - Nov 2023

Thought leader and execution lead for nine practice areas:

• **Investment Portfolio:** Structured build out of investment portfolio using market, SWOT, and objectives and key results analysis (OKR). Developed initiative guardrails with prioritization based on my own formula (Cost of Barriers, see my book).

- **Executable/Integration Portfolio:** Measurable work-item elaboration intended to develop enough signal that it can be executed by delivery teams with confidence. Developed templates effective for quickly elaborating all parts of the backlog taxonomy.
- **Delivery Portfolio:** Developed techniques, tactics, and procedures for enabling parallel work and delivering executable facts with certainty and stability. Expertise in Kanban, Scrum processes, and developing high performing teams using those processes.
- Devops Automation holistic approach from left to right:
 - Helping humans get out of their own way at the exploration level in the value stream. Leading to...
 - o Eliminating need for human intervention using automated build and testing tools at the integration and delivery levels in the value stream.
- Organizational Change Management: Designing organizational operating models, along with facilitating and mapping Prosci ADKAR model to those organizational models. Special emphasis on using starter kata (practice exercises) to replace legacy behaviours and people management with people-centric delivery systems.
- **Training Library:** Author and presenter of complete Agile Product Delivery library, created on behalf of clients. Curated curriculum and samples available on request.
- Assessment Models: Designed and implemented custom, programmable assessments for Delivery Teams, Integration Value Stream Teams, and whole Organization. Samples available on request
- **Technical Coaching**: Coaching software development teams on modern software engineering practices, devsecops, CI/CD, technical excellence, acceptance testing techniques.
- **Taxonomy Design:** According to James, too much runway in the backlog incurs duplicated work. Too little runway ends up throwing a giant snowball at delivery teams. For best value stream flow, James has designed and implemented many backlog taxonomies for F250 organizations.
- **Team Topologies**: Designed teams facing different demands. Some teams require much more upstream preparation to accommodate existing cognitive load. Other teams thrive on more value elaboration mixed with execution. Some teams have highly variable cycle times, so they need to use a kanban approach typically. Other teams consistently deliver a cycle time of one, so they execute as scrum teams. James has expertise in both processes, and will guide team formation using these processes to best match upstream elaboration delivered by product owners.

Additionally:

- Organizational Value Stream design and execution using these five fundamentals:
 - Teams Assembled teams for all levels of the value stream, including leadership Investment teams, Portfolio Integration teams, technical and nontechnical delivery teams.
 - Backlogs substantial experience assembling value elaboration stream backlogs in Rally, ADO, Jira, VersionOne, and manually, all achieving a

- continuous ready state and supporting execution using multiple teams in parallel.
- Working, tested product integration of behavior driven and test driven development to ensure the highest quality increments are available to the delivery pipeline.
- **Flow** Expertise in designing workflows that balance holding costs with transaction costs, and executed using multiple teams working in parallel.
- **Risk Management** Developed robust risk management systems that reinforce transparency and continuous improvement.
- Substantial experience with all major backlog/ALM tools, including ADO, Rally, Jira, VersionONE.
- Guided best practices for Quality, Risk, and Dependency management, meeting government compliance, cloud solutions, manufacturing, security, devops, FFIEC audits, state government IVV reviews.
- Experience with Fed Gate Reviews.
- Experience with Azure Cloud migration.

 Experience setting up Scrum at Scale teams, including Executive Action Team and Executive Metascrum.

Clients include Ford Motor, Dearborn, MI (Feb 2019 - Jun 2021), Northern Trust Bank, Chicago, III (July 2021-Mar 2022), Voya Financial, Remote (Mar 2022- Dec 2022), Citi Bank, Tampa (Dec 2022 - June 2023), ATT, Atlanta (Jul 2023 - Nov 2023).

Owner, Agile Coach, Scrum Master, Grid Sky Consulting May 2015 - Feb 2019 Portfolio, devops, training, strategy and execution consulting for multiple clients. Highlights:

- Instructor, L3/Harris (Feb 2019): Delivery of custom value stream training content.
- Instructor, Scrum Master, Bank of America (Dec 2018 Feb 2019):
 Provided primarily training of transformation for Regulatory Reporting division.
- Enterprise Transformation Coach, CSX Railway (Jan 2017 Dec 2018): Leading full transformation of organization from team to portfolio level. Program includes classroom training, team coaching, leadership portfolio coaching and consulting, organizing communities of practice, coaching of Kanban and Scrum processes, consulting on DevOps pipeline and CI/CD. Coaching and training provided for over 1000 people and 70 teams, with a backlog of 650 projects.
- Executive Practice Officer, Scrum Master, Software Development/Agile Transformation Coach, State of Al. (May 2015 Nov 2017):
 Development manager for \$40m project spanning multiple state agencies, and covered development of Medicaid, CHIP, SNAP, TANF, DHR, Elderly and Disabled applications. Moved legacy mainframe application to Azure cloud with adherence to MITA standards and conditions. To support separation of PHI environments, introduced creation of "Theory of Operations" references for development to operations interface. Introduced Spotify "feature toggle" design pattern. Project was first state in country to get "FedRamp" certification for Azure cloud. Toolchain included .NET, MSFT Dynamics, SQL Server, Golang.

Chief Technical Officer, Scrum Master, Global Treasury Systems May 2011 - May 2015

Oversee development of SmartTreasury treasury management software, which manages cash position, funds transfer, debt and investment, foreign exchange, bank account management.

Experience prior to 2012:

- Lead Developer, TV Media Software, Marketron 2010 2012
- EVP, Security and Encryption Applications, DX Machine, Inc 2005 2009
- CTO, Certified Mail Automation, US Certified Letters 2001 2004

Additional Information

Author, "AGILE V2 COACH'S FIELD MANUAL"

Community Involvement

- Speaker
- Article Author

Competencies/Education

Regulations

• HIPAA, PHI Compliance

Industry Standards and Methods

SSAE 16

Process Know-how

• SCRUM, Kanban Expertise

Education

• University of Alabama, Birmingham